<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More work for the dean in a brief answer to some scandalous reports published by Dr. Stillingfleet in his book entituled, "An impartial account of the history, nature and pleas of the present separation from the communion of the Church of England" against some of the Lords faithful servants, namely, Mr. Henry Barrow, Mr. John Greenwood, Mr. John Penry, who by the bishops means, after long imprisonment, were put to death, contrary to Queen Elizabeths mind; in the year 1593 ... : as likewise here is word for word the petition of those persecuted Christians, wherein is shewed the barbarous usage of the bishops to them : together with the refutation of the then esteemed Bishop of Winchester's blasphemous doctrine, by Mr. Henry Barrow, with the description of the true Church of God, according to Christs Testament, by the whole Church at London, whom the doctor calleth Brownists; with the reason why they were so nick-named by their enemies : very needful for all true Protestants to know / by Thomas Wall.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11773574</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11773574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48903</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 555:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More work for the dean in a brief answer to some scandalous reports published by Dr. Stillingfleet in his book entituled, "An impartial account of the history, nature and pleas of the present separation from the communion of the Church of England" against some of the Lords faithful servants, namely, Mr. Henry Barrow, Mr. John Greenwood, Mr. John Penry, who by the bishops means, after long imprisonment, were put to death, contrary to Queen Elizabeths mind; in the year 1593 ... : as likewise here is word for word the petition of those persecuted Christians, wherein is shewed the barbarous usage of the bishops to them : together with the refutation of the then esteemed Bishop of Winchester's blasphemous doctrine, by Mr. Henry Barrow, with the description of the true Church of God, according to Christs Testament, by the whole Church at London, whom the doctor calleth Brownists; with the reason why they were so nick-named by their enemies : very needful for all true Protestants to know / by Thomas Wall.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Mischief of separation.</term>
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Plaine refutation of M. Giffard's book, intitled, A short treatise against the Donatistes of England.</term>
               <term>Greenwood, John, d. 1593.</term>
               <term>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>More Work FOR THE DEAN.</p>
            <p>In a Brief Anſwer to ſome Scandalous Reports, Publiſhed by Dr. <hi>STILLINGFLEET,</hi> in his Book, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>An Impartial Account of the Hiſtory, Nature and Pleas of the preſent Separation from the Communion of the Church of</hi> England; againſt ſome of the Lords faithful Servants, namely, Mr. <hi>Henry Barrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Greenwood,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Penry,</hi> who by the Biſhops means, after long Impriſonment, were put to death, contrary to Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> mind, in the year 1593, becauſe they refuſed. Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of the many Popiſh Corruptions in the Miniſtry, and Worſhip retained therein: And alſo for bearing their Teſtimony againſt the ſame; which is ſtill the Cauſe many Thouſand Proteſtants refuſe Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> at this day.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe here is word for word the Petition of thoſe perſecuted Chriſtians, wherein is ſhewed the Barbarous Uſage of the Biſhops to them.</p>
            <p>Together with the Refutation of the then Eſteemed Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi>'s Blaſphemous Doctrine, by Mr. <hi>Henry Barrow;</hi> with the Deſcription of the true Church of God, according to Chriſts Teſtament, by the whole Church at <hi>London,</hi> whom the Doctor calleth <hi>Browniſts;</hi> with the reaſon why they were ſo Nick-named by their Enemies. Very needful for all true Proteſtants to know.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Wall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prov. 31. 8. <hi>Open thy mouth for the dumb, in the cauſe of all ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are appointed to deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Noble and Sincere hearted Proteſtants, Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>IT may ſeem a thing very ſtrange in nature for a Lamb, without fear, to meet a Lyon in the open field: As it was in Little <hi>David,</hi> when by faith he Encountered with great <hi>Goliah;</hi> the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of the <hi>Pbliſtines;</hi> even ſo it may ſeem ſtrange to ſome, that ſo mean an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall without fear meet. Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet,</hi> fo great a Champion, in the open field. But ſeeing he hath, with <hi>Goliah,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed or deſied that little flock of Chriſt's faithful Servants, the heavenly Armies of the living God; therefore I cannot keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, having, with <hi>David,</hi> the Lord on my ſide; his Truth for my Sword and Buckler; therefore for the Honour of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and love I bear to all his Servants, I ſhall herein defend the Rights and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of my Lord and Saviour; That he is the only Archbiſhop, Lord Spiritual, and Lawgiver to his Church, in all things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb facs="tcp:48903:3"/> to the worſhip of his Father; And ſhall ſtand by the ſame teſtimony which any of the Lords Servants have born againſt the Doctor, and all the Canons of his Church to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Among all the Enemies of Gods people, the moſt wicked'ſt are thoſe that under the Viſage of Chriſtianity, would be reckoned among the Lords Proteſtant people; in word, declaring they are on Chriſts ſide, but in their Works and Writings ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their hatred againſt him, and all his faithful Servants, for no other cauſe, but by manifeſting their love to Chriſt, in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Commandment in Gods Worſhip, and bearing their teſtimony againſt all mens inventions to the contrary: ſuch an enemy hath the Doctor manifeſted himſelf to be to the Chriſtians herein mentioned, in the falſe Reports publiſhed againſt them, to the Defamation of their perſons, their Writings, and the Truth they profeſſed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, as is hereafter plainly diſcovered concerning their Faith in the Deſcription of the true Church of God, with all her Officers, and in what order Chriſt hath commanded in his Teſtament, for them
<pb facs="tcp:48903:3"/> to walk therein, with Church. State Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, together with its holy Order, I deſire the Doctor to compare with his Church and Miniſtry, and then declare to the world, which he believeth in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is the true Church of God. If God be pleaſed to open his eyes, and carry him above all earthly Wiſdom, by his Spirit, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an exceeding high Mountain, the height <note place="margin">Rev. 21. 10.</note> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to behold the City filled with the glory of God; and unleſs God doth be his <note place="margin">Ezek. 17. 22, 23. &amp; 40. 2. Rev. 21. 11. Eccl. 10. 15.</note> help, he, with the Apoſtate <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> will ſtill weary himſelf, and not know how to find the way to the City; in which City, by the Canon or holy Rules thereof, Chriſt hath appointed for her Officers, Paſtors, Teachers, Elders and Deacons, <hi>Epheſ. 4.</hi> But the 7th Canon of the Doctors Church ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall affirm, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Church by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Archdeacons, and the reſt that do bear office, is Antichriſtian, or repugnant to the word of God, let him be excommunicated ipſo facto, and ſo continue, until he repent, and publickly revoke his wicked Errors.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus hath appointed the whole form of Goſpel-worſhip to be learned out of his
<pb facs="tcp:48903:4"/> Teſtament, and that it be agreeable to the <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 20. Act. 20. 27.</note> ſame, upon pain of all the Curſes in Gods Book, to him that addeth or diminiſheth to <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18. Prov. 30. 6.</note> or from. But the <hi>4th</hi> Canon of the Doctors Church ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall affirm, that the form of Gods worſhip, eſtabliſhed by Law, and contained in the book of Common-prayer, is a corrupt and ſuperſtitious, or unlawful worſhip of God, or containeth any thing in it that is repugnant to the Scriptures, let him be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated ipſo facto,</hi> and ſuch like, wherein is preferred the Traditions and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of men to be equal to the inſpired Rules in Chriſts Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Now let me ask the Doctor, whether he believeth in his conſcience, that when he cometh to appear before the Lord Jeſus, the chief Judg, that he ſhall be judged for the breach of his Church Canons, or for the breach of Chriſts Canons, in his Teſtament; ſeeing the word of God telleth us, that whatſoever man that hath engaged himſelf to be a worſhipper of God, and ſhall break the holy Rules in Worſhip he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to keep; and after Gods order, by brethren, uſed for his recovery, <hi>Matth. 18.</hi> if he ſtand obſtinate, then that which the
<pb facs="tcp:48903:4"/> Church, by the Rules of Chriſt, doth by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating him on earth, is confirmed in heaven: but the curſe for the breach of mans Canons in worſhip, though pretended to God in worſhip, is the curſe cauſeleſs, which ſhall not come, <hi>Prov. 26. 2.</hi> But the curſe turn'd into a bleſſing, upon all that do, <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 11.</note> to wit, the Commandments of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: they only have right to the Tree of life, and may enter in through the gates in the City. So that it is not enough for the Doctor to think it is ſufficient for him, or his hearers to believe verbally that Chriſt is the Son of God come in the fleſh, as the only founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion; but they that do expect ſalvation by Chriſts Merits, muſt not only believe he is the Son of God, but by their obedience confeſs the ſame, that as a Son was he faithful in his houſe or Church, as <hi>Moſes</hi> the Prophet, like unto <hi>Moſes</hi> the only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver for Goſpel worſhip, as aforeſaid; which the Doctor doth not obediently believe, ſo long as he retaineth the Popiſh Office of a Dean, for one of Chriſts Goſpel-Miniſters, as though Chriſt was not wiſe enough to give Titles fit for his Miniſters. But as we read of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, that woman which ſitteth
<pb facs="tcp:48903:5"/> upon a ſear let coloured beaſt, full of the names of blaſphemy: this name Dean pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from thence, may be reckoned among them, <hi>Rev. 13. 1.</hi> &amp; 17. 3.</p>
            <p>And, laſtly, as every true Chriſtian muſt not only believe that Chriſt is the Son of God come in the fleſh, but alſo they muſt walk in him, rooted and eſtabliſhed, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt by the example of the Primitive Churches commended in them: As when <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> had gone from the pure keeping in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to God, his Ordinances, and the <hi>Cove-Hant</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>of Levi,</hi> the call of the Lord to them, to reform their ways by the prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> was to <hi>remember the Law of Moſes,</hi> and not <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 4.</note> the Tradition, or Canons of men: and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this was done, they that feared the Lord had ſeparated from them, and ſpake often one to another, and a book of remembrance was <note place="margin">Iſa. 42. 4.</note> written for them, that thought on his Name, even his Law, and partook not in the evil of the tranſgreſſors. Even ſo, when after the long <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 21.</note> Apoſtacy of Chriſtians, the Lord called them to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to reform their <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 4.</note> ways, but not by the Canons of men, but by the everlaſting Goſpel, taught by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God in King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48903:5"/> King <hi>James,</hi> and in King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>1ſt</hi> and <hi>2d.</hi> to this day; and until this work be done, all that <hi>fear the Lord do ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves, and ſpeak often one to another:</hi> for which they are and were ſtill perſecuted, reproached and defamed; but by whom but by the Devil, called the <hi>Dragon</hi> and <hi>Serpent,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 10.</note> in his ſervants, out of whoſe mouths comes floods of teproaches to deſtroy the woman, <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 15.</note> had not the earth then, and ſtill doth by more than an ordinary Providence help the woman, in drinking up, or rather hindering the work <note place="margin">Verſe 16.</note> of perſecution.</p>
            <p>Thus hoping the Doctor will lay theſe things to heart; and who knoweth, ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Adams</hi> Sons ſome men for their malice and fury are compared to Lions, 2 <hi>Tim. 4. 17.</hi> but God in his mercy may give him grace to the changing of his fierce nature. If the Lord by the Arrows of his Truth prick his heart, <hi>Pſal. 45. 5. Acts 2. 37. Heb. 4. 12.</hi> that ſo he may yield obedience to Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and lie down with the Lambs in the Lords holy Mountain, even Sion his true Church, <hi>Iſa. 11. 7. Heb. 12. 22.</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>the Lords people ſhall be all Righteous, Iſa. 60. wiſe as Serpents, harmleſs as Doves,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48903:6"/> 
               <hi>men in underſtanding, children in malice,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. for ſuch only can have right to enter into the Kingdom of God, <hi>Mat. 18. 3.</hi> that ſo he may for the time to come ſee himſelf in the glaſs of Gods word new born, all his fleſhly glory and honour fading away by the Spirit of God blowing on him; ſo ſhall he beat his ſword of bitter words into plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheares, that by the word of God the fallow ground of his uncircumciſed heart be broken up, the ſeed of Gods truth ſowed therein watred by the heavenly dew of his grace, that he may bring forth the fruits of righteouſneſs, <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 18. Heb. 12. 14.</note> which is peace with all men, and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the face of God; which is and ſhall be the prayers for the very enemies of him who is the Lords unworthy ſervant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wall,</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48903:7"/>
            <head>More Work FOR THE DEAN: Or, A brief ANSWER To ſome Scandalous Reports publiſhed by Dr. Stillingfleet, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THerefore among the many ſore Travels King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> beheld among the Sons of men, this, ſaith he, is one, <hi>That for every right work a man is envied of his neighbour,</hi> Eccleſ. 4. 4. Pſal. 106. 16. Numb. 11. 29. Matt. 26. 7, 8, 9, 10. Now if that were a right work in the Lords Servants of old, in call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords people out of the temporal <hi>Babylon,</hi> to ſeparate themſelves from all the filthineſs of thoſe Heathens, <hi>Ezra. 6. 21.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48903:8"/> that they might enter into Covenant with the Lord, to ſerve or worſhip him, as he had given commandment by the hand of <hi>Moſe's</hi> both in Miniſtry, Ordinances and Order, for which work they were envied of their Neighbours, <hi>Nehem. 4</hi> and 5 Chapters; even ſo it was a-like right work in theſe latter days, for the Lords Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to call his elected ones out of the Romiſh Sodomy, Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Spiritual <hi>Babylon, Rev. 11. 8.</hi> and 18. 4. that they might ſeparate themſelves from their abominable filthineſs in worſhip and nature, that ſo with the Lord they might enter into the Covenant of the Goſpel, <hi>Acts 2. 47. 2 Cor. 11. 2. Iſa 62. 5. Ezek. 16 8.</hi> to worſhip him as the Son of God, Chriſt Jeſus, had appointed in his laſt Will and Teſtament, both in Miniſtry, Ordinances, Time and Order; and for this right work, among others, was Mr. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> Mr. <hi>Greenwood,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> envied then to death by their Neighbours, and now again, after their death, envied by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> to the deſamation of the memory <hi>(Prov. 10. 7.)</hi> of thoſe whom God had bleſſed, and are now at reſt in the Lord, <hi>Rev. 14. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The evil way this Doctor hath taken to vent his envy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe Servants of God, is, firſt, in calling their Books ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; and therefore becauſe he could not prove it, he is driven to make uſe of the falſe reports of their Enemies, ſuch as never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt the ſucceſſion of their Miniſtry received from the Biſhops, nor yet their vain School Titles of Batchelor in Divinity, a Title not found in Chriſts Teſtament, ſet in the front of that Book called the <hi>Bloody Tenet,</hi> out of which Book, the Doctor tells us, that Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> ſaid, Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> told him, that when Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> was under the Gibbet, he lift up his eyes and ſaid, <hi>If I be deceived, thou haſt deceived me.</hi> To which I anſwer, If Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> did ſay thoſe words, it might be draw<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n from him upon the ſame occaſion the like words, were drawn from the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> when the Prieſts and falſe Prophets ſeeing his conſtancy and faithfulneſs in the Lords meſſage againſt their evil doings <hi>(Jer. 20. 8, 10.)</hi> derided him, which occaſioned him to ſay, <hi>O Lord thou haſt deceived me, and I was deceived, thou art ſtronger than I, and haſt prevailed: I am in deriſion dayly, every one mocketh me.</hi> Even ſo ſome of the Clergy being preſent when Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> ſuffered death, ſeeing his conſtant, teſtimony againſt their evil doings, might deride him, and ſo might occaſion thoſe words from him. Surely if the Doctor had had any thing worth noting againſt this man, a few Pages in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48903:8"/> his Book ſhould not have contained it: Thus all may ſee, it is more of malice than of any juſt matter he had againſt him. And why at this time? Becauſe the memory of Mr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>Greenwood,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> was lately revived in a Chriſtian Warning-piece, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Kings Majeſty laſt <hi>April;</hi> ſo that if Mr. <hi>Barrows</hi> Books therein mentioned, ſhould be again ſought after, which doth ſo live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover the abomination of that Miniſtry of which the Doctor is one, therefore he hath endeavoured to diſgrace their perſons, that their labours might not be regarded; and therefore it will not be amiſs by the way, to note what Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> hath written, in one of his Books called the <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> which the Doctor called ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, for comparing the true Miniſtry of Chriſt and the Miniſtry of Antichriſt together; that as light maketh manifeſt, ſo in laying down Chriſts true Miniſtry, the abomination of all other by it may be diſcovered; of which ſubject in particular, Mr. <hi>Barrows</hi> words are theſe in his <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> page 46.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſtry appointed by Chriſt unto the Government of Church be of two ſorts, Elders and Deacons,</hi> Phil. 1. 1. 1 Tim. 3. Tit. 1. 5. Rom. 12. Acts 20. 28. 1 Tim. 5. 17. 1 Cor. 12. 7, 8. Acts 6. <hi>The Elders, ſome of them to give attendance unto the publick Miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments, as the Paſtor and Teacher; the other Elders together with them, to give attendance to the publick Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. The Deacons office, to attend to the gathering and diſtributing the Contribution of the Church, for the maintenance of the Miniſtry and Poor,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.</p>
            <p>Now (ſaith Mr. <hi>Barrow)</hi> to come to the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is ſo manifold and divers as I know not how to begin to deſcribe it; but let it firſt be divided in theſe three ſorts: 1. Reigning or governing. 2. Serving; and 3 Collegiate. 1. Of the reigning and governing Miniſters, are Arch biſhops, Lord Biſhops, Arch Deacons, Chancellors, Commiſſaries, all of the High Commiſſion; as likewiſe ſuch Civil Doctors, Proctors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, Scribes, Purſevants, Sumners, as attend upon their Courts of Faculties, Prerogative Archees, Delegates. 2. Of the ſerving ſort are, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, Hireling Lecturies, Vagrant and Mercenary Preachers, Houſe prieſts, Chaplains, half prieſts, or Catechiſers, Churchwardens, Side men, Queſt-men, Pariſh-Clarks. 3. Of the miniſtry Collegiate, are Lord Biſhops, Deans, Sub deans, Prebendaries, Canons, Petit Canons, Goſpellers, Epiſtlers, Singing-men, Singing boys, Vergers, Sextons. This diviſion, I ſuppoſe, will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48903:9"/> well near ſuffice for their Officers. But now how to divide or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh their Offices, I know not, I am ſo unlearned and ignorant of ſuch great ſecrets and high myſteries; neither yet have I skill to marſhal them in their degrees of honour which I have heard ſay they have both in the Commonwealth and in their Schools, as their Primate, their Metropolitan Graces, their Palatine Lord Biſhops, and their Barony Lordſhips, all which I wene be Peers of the Realm and Eſtates of the Land. Now there are alſo certain Doctors of Divinity, and Batchellors of Divinity, which have many great priviledges and prerogatives of the Cap, the Scarlet Gown, the Hood, the Habit, the Tippet, the Ring, the Chair, the one of them being a Knights fellow, the other an Eſquires, in any ground in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> alſo how capable theſe are by Statute of how many Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>Now ſurely this diſcovery doth not a little torment the Doctor, to cauſe him to be ſo malicious againſt <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> to diſgrace him now he is dead, <hi>Papiſt</hi> like, who burnt the bones of ſuch as they call Hereticks, many years after they have murder'd them, when as they did as <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> hath done, that is, bear their teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rabble of Antichriſts miniſtry, as is noted out of the Book of <hi>Martyrs</hi> in the foreſaid Chriſtian Warning-piece to the King p. 23. for what comfort can thoſe have which call themſelves miniſters, and cannot prove their Ordination to be according to Goſpel-order, when at the laſt day they will ſay, <hi>Lord, Lord, we have propheſied in thy name, and caſt out devils in thy name, and have done many wonderous works,</hi> when Chriſt ſhall ſay to them, <hi>I know you not; depart from me ye workers of iniquity?</hi> For is it not ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity for any to take upon them the name of a Dean inſtead of a Paſtor, and to be a perſecutor rather than a preſerver, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods plain Law, to be a tale-bearer, as it written, Levit. 19. 16, 17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not go up and down as a tale bearer among thy people;</hi> yea, to reproach the deceaſed Saints of the Lord calling their Books ſeditious, not only for pleading that the miniſtry ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt might by Proteſtants be embraced, but alſo for reproving the blaſphemous Doctrine of <hi>T. C.</hi> the then eſteemed Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Martin Marprelate,</hi> namely this, that the Orders and Ordinances which Chriſt hath in his Teſtament left unto his Church, were but temporary, whilſt the Church was under Heathen Tyrants; and that where the Goſpel is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48903:9"/> embraced by a Chriſtian Prince, they are not only not neceſſary but inconvenient, yet intollerable, as bringing the utter ſubverſion of the Land, raiſing up rumults and uproars, and withdrawing the people from obedience unto their Magiſtrates. Unto which <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> replieth, that there ought throughout all ages and eſtates of the world, in all places to be one and the ſame form of outward Government in all true Churches of Chriſt unto the worlds end, <hi>ſcil.</hi> that Apoſtolical primitive pattern left unto us in Chriſts Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and none other; which undoubted truth <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops confirms both from the Law and Goſpel, in theſe words. The Lord when he erected his Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnacle among the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> gave them a perfect pattern in all things, even to the leaſt inſtrument, hook, or tape therein, as alſo the whole compoſition of every thing belonging thereunto, with all the Ordinances thereof, and left nothing to the will and diſcretion of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation was, that he was faithful in all his houſe, as a ſervant, for a teſtimony of theſe things that were to be ſpoken after, <hi>Exod. 25. Heb. 8. 5. Heb. 3.</hi> alſo we read of <hi>David</hi> in the diſtribution of the order and functions of the Prieſts and Levites, and likewiſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> in building the material Temple, how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the Lord ſet down the matter, form, number, ſize, place, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and uſe of every thing belonging thereunto, <hi>1 Chron. 28. 11.</hi> as alſo what perfect Laws was given by God for every thing to be done; and likewiſe how jealous the Lord was over his Sanctuary; and what ſevere judgments was upon all them that tranſgreſſed the leaſt of his Ordinances, as is ſeen in <hi>Nadab, Abihu,</hi> Lev. 10. <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, <hi>Numb. 16.</hi> on <hi>Eli</hi> and his ſons, <hi>1 Sam. 4.</hi> and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry the like: Now may we ſuppoſe God is leſs jealous, careful, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident over his glorious Temple of lively ſtones, which conſiſteth of the bodies and ſouls of his Saints, for the ſtructure, inſtruments, form, order, and ordinances, which ſhall abide to the worlds end, than he was of the other which conſiſted but of wood and ſtone, and was to abide but for a time, being but a type and ſhadow of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; if we think ſo, let the New Teſtament convince us, wherein is left unto us a moſt exact, lively, and expreſs pattern for all things concerning the miniſtry, ordinances, maintenance, time, and order; therefore Chriſt is ſaid to be faithful <hi>(Heb. 3. 6.)</hi> in his own houſe as a Son, who is the head of his body the Church <hi>(Col. 1. 18.)</hi> of the living God, the only Lord ſpiritual and Archbiſhop of their ſoul, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 25.</hi> If the Dr. be, as may be ſuppoſed he is of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48903:10"/> Biſhops mind, by imbracing an Office not once named in Chriſts <hi>Teſtament,</hi> to wit, a Dean, by it allowing that the Orders ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt were but temporary; ſo that Chriſts Offices of Paſtors, Teachers, Elders and Deacons, is not allowed by the Doctor to remain perpetual: When he hath proved it, he may be believed; and until then, Mr. <hi>Barrows</hi> teſtimony herein is truth, and the contrary ſeditious: And they that own any other Miniſtry, Order, or Ordinances in Goſpel-worſhip than Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, is intollerable, to the utter ſubverſion of all good orders in Chriſts Church, and precurer of the Judgments to come on that Land. Now if the Doctor will not believe this to be a truth, though a truth proved by Scripture, becauſe thoſe he calleth <hi>Browniſts</hi> declare it; I hope he will believe it, if ſome of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his own Church ſaith it in the Admonition to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the Thirteenth year of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign; they in oppoſition to the Miniſtry of Arch and Lord Biſhops declare in the Epiſtle, Either we muſt have a right <hi>(Matt 9. 37 Eph. 4. 11, 12)</hi> Miniſtry of God, a right Government of his Church, <hi>Matt. 18. 15, 16, 17.</hi> according to the Scriptures, both which we lack; or elſe there can be no right Religion, nor yet from the contempt thereof, can Gods Plagues be from us any while deferred. And further, they ſay in Page 2. We allow and like well of Popiſh Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, men for all ſeaſons, King <hi>Henries</hi> Prieſts, Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Prieſts, who of a truth, if Gods Word were preciſely kept, ſhould from the ſame be utterly removed. Now to leave this to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors conſideration, I ſhall in the next place better inform the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor what end <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> made that ſo the Doctor may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to own his falſe report in his Book.</p>
            <p>I find in a book Printed a little after <hi>Mr. Barrows</hi> death, in the year 1593, Intituled <hi>Henry Barrow's Platform,</hi> by reaſon of ſome things <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> had Written, was after his death Printed: In which, the Publiſher declareth in theſe words, A Gentleman of a good Houſe told me, that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> asked the Learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Raynols</hi> what he then thought of thoſe Two men <hi>Henry Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>John Greenwood?</hi> he anſwered her Majeſty, that it could not avail any thing to ſhew his judgment concerning them, ſeeing they were put to death; and being loath to ſpeak his mind further, Her Majeſty charged him upon his Allegiance to ſpeak; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he anſwered, that he was perſwaded, if they had lived, they would have been Two as worthy Inſtruments for the Church of God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48903:10"/> as hath been raiſed up in this Age. Her <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſighed and ſaid no more. But after that ſhe riding to a Park near the place where they ſuffered death, called again to mind their ſuffering of death; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to take farther information concerning them, demanded of the Earl of <hi>Cumberland</hi> who was preſent when they ſuffered, What end they made? He anſwered, A very godly end, and prayed for your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>State:</hi> moreover ſaith the ſame Author, <hi>Mr. Philips,</hi> a preacher famous, both ſeeing and hearing <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> his holy ſpeeches and preparations for death, ſaid, <hi>Barrow! Barrow! my ſoul be with thine.</hi> By all which it appeareth, that this report which the Doctor hath taken out of <hi>Mr. Cotton</hi>'s book, printed above 40. years after their death; and then, but that Mr. <hi>Cotten</hi> ſhould ſay Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> told him ſo, is very falſe; and the rather to be believed it was falſe, becauſe Mr. <hi>Cotten,</hi> though he went into <hi>New England,</hi> yet could never forſake the order of his miniſtry recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Biſhops, nor yet glorying in their vain School titles, as in the title of his book afore noted, he ſtileth himſelf <hi>John Cotten</hi> Batchellor in Divinity. Theſe fleſhly titles <hi>Paul</hi> was aſhamed of, and accounted them but dung, though he had as many to glory in, as any man, <hi>Phil. 3.</hi> all which Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> reproved, which <hi>Mr. Cotten</hi> did not like, therefore could report a hearſay againſt <hi>Mr. Barrow,</hi> though no more diſhonour to Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> nor the cauſe he dyed for, than it was to the prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Jer. 20. and the cauſe he ſuffered for; both for the good old way of the Lord, under the Law, the other under the Goſpel-worſhip.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the Doctor is pleaſed to publiſh againſt <hi>Mr. Penry,</hi> That <hi>Mr. Hilderſham</hi> ſhould tell <hi>Mr. Cotten,</hi> both miniſters of the biſhops order, that <hi>Mr. Penry</hi> ſhould ſay a little before his death, <hi>That he had deſerved death at the Queens hands, for that he had ſeduced many of her loyal ſubjects to a ſeparation from hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word of life in the Pariſh Churches; which though himſelf had learned to diſcern the evil of, yet could he never recover divers of her Majeſties ſubjects whom he had ſeduced.</hi> To which I anſwer, as the wiſe man ſaith, Prov. 18. 17. <hi>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth juſt; but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</hi> Now by ſearch I find that report cannot in the leaſt meaſure be true: Firſt, being but the report of his enemy; and why his enemy, but as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was to ſome in the Church of <hi>Galatia,</hi> for telling them the truth, <hi>Gal. 4. 16. 1 King. 22. 8.</hi> Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> as well as <hi>Mr. Barrow,</hi> teſtified againſt <hi>Mr. Hilderſham</hi>'s miniſtry, which teſtimony I ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48903:11"/> eaſily prove he maintained to his death, as appeareth by the conſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his faith, his Letter to the Church at <hi>London</hi> he was a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of. 3. His Letter to his Wife, all written near that time of his death. In his Confeſſion he thus declareth himſelf: <hi>I deteſt againſt the Pope, his triple crown, his uſurped juriſdiction of either of both ſwords. I deteſt the limbs of that body, their ſpiritual power, as Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Archbiſhops, Lord Biſhops, Suffragans, Abbots, Friers, Deans</hi> (this word <hi>Dean</hi> may vex the Dr.) <hi>Arch deacons, Commiſſaries, Officials, Monks, Canons, Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bends Prieſts.</hi> Beſides this teſtimony, which is ſufficient to prove the report falſe Mr. <hi>Hilderſham</hi> raiſed againſt Mr. <hi>Penry,</hi> let me here add what Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> wrote to the Church at <hi>London</hi> whereof he was a member, in theſe words, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, let us think our lot and portion more than happy or bleſſed, that now we are vouchſafed the favour not only to know and profeſs, but alſo to ſuffer for the ſincerity of the Goſpel: let us remember, that great is our reward in heaven, if we endure unto the end. I teſtifie unto you for mine own part, as I ſhall anſwer before Jeſus Chriſt and his elect Angels, that I never ſaw any truth more clear and undoubted, than this witneſs wherein we ſtand, firſt, againſt falſe Offices. 2. Callings. 3. Works. 4 Maintenance left and retained in the Land; and I thank my God I am not only ready to be bound and baniſhed, but even to dye in this cauſe by his ſtrength. Yea, my brethren, I greatly long in regard of my ſelf, to be diſſolved, and to live in the bleſſed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven. Thus having from my heart with tears performed, it may be my laſt duty towards you all in this life, and remember to ſtand fat and faithful in Jeſus Chriſt, as you have received him unto your immortality; and confirm and eſtabliſh you to the end, for the praiſe of his glory, Amen. The 24th of the 4th month,</hi> April, 1593. He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd death <hi>May 24.</hi> next after.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe be not, with his former teſtimonies, ſufficient to clear Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> from the Doctors calumniations, all written (we ſee) a little before his death; I ſhall add a third teſtimony, which as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>a threeſold cord is not eaſily broken;</hi> even the laſt words to his Wife, when cloſe priſoner, looking every day to be carried to the place of Execution, all in print preſently after his death, and yet to be ſeen at this day, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To my beloved Wife,</hi> Hellen or Penry, <hi>partaker with me in this life of the ſufferings of the Goſpel, in the kingdom and patience of Jeſus Chriſt, and reſting with me in undoubted hope of the glory that ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48903:11"/> be revealed; all ſtrength, comfort, with all other ſpiritual bleſſings, be multiplied through</hi> Jeſus, Chriſt <hi>our Lord, I ſee, my beloved, my blood is layed for, ſo my days and teſtimony is drawing to an end, for ought I know; and therefore you ſo dear a ſiſter, and ſo loving a wife in the Lord, as you have been unto me: firſt then I beſeech you ſtand faſt in the truth which you and I profeſs at this preſent in much outward diſcomfort and danger; let your ſoul and your body be far from thoſe Aſſemblies which yield either known or ſecret ſubmiſſion unto the ordinance of the beaſt; that is, to receive his marks either in the right hand, or in the forehead, as the ſpirit of God ſaith,</hi> Rev 13. 16. <hi>for this are you forbidden to do under the pain of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal wrath,</hi> Rev. 14. 9, 10, 11. 2 Cor. 6. 14, 15. 16. 1 Cor. 3. 16, 17. Rev. 22 18, 19. Deut. 12. 30, 31, 32. <hi>Again, my beloved continue a member of the holy ſociety whereof you and I are, where the Lord in his Ordinances reigneth; for here, and in all ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies the Lord dwelleth by his preſence and power of his ſpirit,</hi> Mat. 18. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>and 28. 20. and 29. 45 Lev. 26. 11, 12 <hi>here he is a mighty protector and defonce ready at hand,</hi> Iſa 26. 1. and 4. 6. <hi>and his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances you know hath. he greatly commanded to be kept and obſerved,</hi> Pſal. 119. 14. 1 Cor. 11. 1. 1 Tim. 6. 14. <hi>and the loving-kindneſs of the Eternal is for ever and ever towards them and their ſeed that remember to do them,</hi> Pſal. 103. 17, 18. <hi>whereas all thoſe are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that err from his ſtatutes, and diminiſh from the obedience they owe unto his Majeſty,</hi> Pſal. 119. 2. Rev. 22. 9. Pſal. 119 118. <hi>I pray you work all theſe places, with all ſuch like in the word againſt thoſe that make a ſlight matter either to walk in the ways of God, or to be ſubject to ſmall corruptions, as they account them. Be armed with the power of the word againſt all ſuch lying deluſions,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 14, 15. 2 Theſ. 2. 9. <hi>In concluſion, my dear wife and ſiſter, look not at any earthly thing; conſecrate your ſelf wholly both body and ſoul, husband, children, and whatſoever you have, unto the Lord your God, let them not be dearer unto you than his worſhip and ſervice; know it, know it to be an unſpeakable preferment for you that he vouchſafed to take either your ſelf or any of yours to ſuffer affliction with him and his Goſpel here on earth,</hi> Luke 8 29, 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 29. <hi>I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that you have undergone the profeſſion of the truth ſet down by our Saviour,</hi> Luke 14. 26, 27. <hi>that is, to hate all in reſpect of his Goſpel: fear not want of outward things, for the Lord careth for you and yours: remember what is ſet down</hi> Heb. 11. 5. Luk. 12. 31. <hi>the Lord is my God, and yours, and the God of our ſeed.</hi> Thus with many
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48903:12"/> ſweet and heavenly admonitions and advice, he ſaith, <hi>I got means this day to write thus much unto you, whereof no creature knoweth: therefore in great haſte, with many tears, yet in great ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of ſoul, your husband now for a ſeaſon, and your beloved brother for evermore</hi> John Penry, <hi>an unworthy ſoldier ſure of the victory in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 57. Rev. 12. 11. <hi>ſalute the whole Church from me, eſpecially thoſe in bonds,</hi> meaning thoſe 56. members of the Church in <hi>London</hi> taken on a Lords day as they were ſerving God.</p>
            <p>Now of the barbarous uſage they ſuſtained by the biſhops, I ſhall after herein ſet down word for word as themſelves have declared in a Petition they preſented then to the Parliament. In the mean time let me beſeech the Chriſtian Reader impartially to judg by this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Mr. <hi>Penry</hi> left behind him, yet to be ſeen, though printed in the year he ſuffered, whether that Report the Doctor hath publiſhed to defame a worthy ſervant of Chriſt, for no other cauſe but becauſe he as well as other of the Lords ſervants, contended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the miniſtry of lordly Prelates, not once named in Chriſts te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and that Proteſt ants ſhould not perſwade themſelves they were true worſhippers of God, until they had expelled out from among them the many corruptions in miniſtry and ordinances; the neglect of which good work ſtill calleth for the judgments of God to come on the Nation, as was in a ſecond Warning piece a few months ago proved to be the chief cauſe ſtill why God is bringing his ſevere judgments on theſe three Proteſtant Nations, preſented to the late Parliament.</p>
            <p>And now to add to all the former cauſes of Gods judgments threatned to follow Mr. <hi>Hilderſham</hi>'s footſteps, the Doctor is not content to ſatisfie himſelf with that falſe report, but to imitate him in publiſhing that ſcandalous name <hi>Browniſt</hi> on all thoſe people; unto which ſcandalous name, to ſhew the Doctor his falſe, or rather his malicious ſpirit, in ſaying Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> was one of thoſe people, I ſhall here for the Readers ſatisfaction ſet down what Anſwer to this Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> Paſtor of the people, returned to <hi>Mr. Hilderſham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jacob,</hi> both the Biſhops miniſters. <q rend="margQuotes">As for the name <hi>Browniſt</hi> by which we are reproached, the primitive Chriſtians were by the Prieſts and Phariſees called a Sect of <hi>Nazarens.</hi> Acts 24. 5. every where ſpoken againſt, <hi>Acts</hi> the 28. 22. as at this day Proteſtants are by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> called <hi>Calviniſts, Zuinglians, Heu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48903:12"/> 2dly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> from whom this by-word was taken, is Miniſter of Mr. <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Church, and ſo of Mr. <hi>Hilderſhams,</hi> all Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and not of ours; yet hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as we hear in his Judgment, the truth we profeſs, but for his practice in Worſhip, rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineth ſtill in Apoſtacy, wherein they are.</q> So then, not we, but Mr. <hi>Jacob</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hilderſham</hi> may, if any, be called <hi>Browniſts.</hi> See <hi>Francis Johnſon</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> Intituled, <hi>A Treatiſe of the Church of</hi> England, page 2. And <hi>A Treatiſe of the Miniſtry of</hi> England, <hi>in Anſwer to Mr.</hi> Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham, page 94.</p>
            <p>Moreover, becauſe Doctor <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> durſt not in his Conſcience fight againſt the Cauſe of God theſe Servants of Chriſt maintained after the way of plain dealing, therefore fighteth covertly, under the Banner of other men, yet of the ſame mind with himſelf; and among the many, Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> another Miniſter of the Biſhops ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, whom he maketh one of his chief Armor-bearers (in this railing fight, Dragon like, with floods of reproaches againſt Gods Servants which keeps the Commandments of God, and have (in their Writings) the Teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev. 12. 16.</hi> And it was not ſo bitter then, but it would be as bad now (if the earth did not by more than by an ordinary providence help the Church, the Woman, <hi>Rev. 12. 15.)</hi> Moreover, this man, the Doctor, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, maketh no leſs than Eight times mention of Mr. <hi>Gifford,</hi> in Twelve Leaves of his Book, againſt the forenamed Chriſtians. Now if he would have the world believe, that what Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> hath wrote againſt them to be as Oracles, undeniable truths, ſurely I may, by the ſame Rule, deſire all men likewiſe to believe that to be a truth what Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> hath wrote againſt the Doctors Church and Miniſtry; and the rather to believe in the latter, becauſe who can tell better the evil of their ways, than he who was a Bird in the ſame Cage of confuſion with them? <hi>Rev. 18. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Giffords</hi> words are theſe, <q rend="margQuotes">Through want and abſence of a ſincere Miniſtry, there is a flood of ignorance and darkneſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing the Land for the moſt part; the fear of God is baniſhed from the greateſt part: The wonderful heaps and piles of ſin which ſhould be waſhed away by the Word do undoubtedly cry aloud in the ears of the Lord for vengeance upon the whole Realm. The Devil, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is content thoſe Preachers ſhould ride upon his back, becauſe he is ſure they will ſpur-gaul him but a little, they be very gentle Riders. Do you not think, if they ſhould ſet forth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48903:13"/> Gods word as they ought, and ſpread the Light, that all wicked men, of which their Pariſhes be full, would ſtorm and fret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? The Devil himſelf would fisk about if they ſpur gaul him but a little; but they can tell a ſmooth tail in the Pulpit, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſome merry Story for to make the people merry, or elſe ſome old rotten. Allegory, or ſome far-ſet matter out of ſome great Writer, that their people might be at their wits end to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire them: A man would think to ſee the people come out of the Church blowing, that they were fed as full as ticks, when they go home with empty Bellies: This I dare warrant you; if it be not ſo let me loſe both my ears, go through the Pariſhes of theſe Learned Divines, and except ſuch as fetch their Victuals other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ye ſhall not find Five among Five-ſcore able to underſtand the neceſſary grounds and principles of Religion; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, the people will ſay, they be excellent deep men; but I love not thoſe Wells that a man can draw no Water out of them: See Mr. <hi>Giffords</hi> Book Intituled <hi>Country Divinity,</hi> noted by <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> in his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoyſon,</hi> page 101.</q> Thus it is to be hoped, if the Doctor cannot refute this Teſtimony, he will never hereafter ſpeak againſt the forenamed Chriſtians Teſtimony, which in this particular ſaid no other thing in effect, concerning the Doctors Church and Miniſtry, than Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Doctor is not ſatisfied to ſhoot his Arrows of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words againſt the Ancient Seperation, but, through their ſides, againſt all the Nonconformiſts in this day, envying at their due birthrights and priviledges given them of God and man in freedom to ſerve the Lord, as they are inlightened; and if in any thing, as doubtleſs none but cometh ſhort in a perfect underſtanding in all things how they ought to walk with God, the Doctors duty was then to have by the evidence of Gods written Word, wherein they failed, in the ſpirit of Love to have better informed their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and not as an enemy (to his diſſenting brethren as he calleth them) to infinuate into the Magiſtrates minds, by publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the world, that Liberty of Concience hath occaſioned the growth of Poperty in this Nation, but how greatly hath the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors heart deceived him in this as in the former, is not my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only; that the occaſion of the growth of Popery is by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſo many corruptions retained in his Miniſtry and Worſhip in his Church, as is noted in the Two Chriſtian Warning pieces, one to the King, the other to the late Parliament; but it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48903:13"/> by his Right hand man, and chief Armor bearer in this Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel againſt the Lords Servants, Mr. <hi>Gifford,</hi> in a Dialogue between a Papiſt and a Proteſtant; in the Epiſtle Dedicatory, word for word thus ſet down by <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi> in his <hi>Counterpoyſon,</hi> page 19.</p>
            <p>Some do wonder how it ſhould come to paſs, that among us there ſhould be ſo many, which being born ſince the Goſpel was reſtored in this Land, are ſo zealouſly addicted to Popery which they never did know, and ſo utter enemies to the Goſpel which they, hear; but if they weigh the cauſe of this deadly miſchief, they would ceaſe wondering, and rather wonder that there be no more: For how can it be, ſo long as there be ſo many abuſes in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, but that many ſhall ſtumble and loath the Goſpel? for from hence, as it is manifeſt, the chief cauſe of this evil doth ſpring.</p>
            <p>True it is that our miniſtry doth fight againſt them, but in ſuch ſort that it doth greatly encreaſe them, ſeeming and pretending to tread upon theſe Cockatrice eggs for to break them, and to deſtroy utterly the Viperous generation; when as indeed they ſit upon them, and ſo hatch the brood of this evil kind, and bring them forth in great plenty: for behold a number cry out againſt Popery, and proclaim utter defiance in ſpeech; but their doings are ſuch that for every one they convert to the Goſpel, they cauſe an hundred to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt, to be hardned in their errors, or to fall into flat Atheiſm, while many contrary to the profeſſion which they made, when they entred, ſetting aſide the care of ſouls; not eſteeming nor regarding what became of them ſtudy moſt how to climb high and to ſatisfie their ambitious deſires of honour, raking together Livings cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ouſly and greedily, not caring who feed the flock, ſo they may come by the fleece. Moreover the door hath been opened alſo to let into the Church a rout and ſwarm of ſuch as are more like the prieſts of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> than miniſters of the Goſpel, not only unlearned Idols, which have mouths and ſpeak not; which being weary of their occupation, and covet to live eaſily, and to that end entred, but alſo riotous, dicers, gameſters, quaffers, quarrellers, adulterers, and ſuch like: if the matter were ſecret, I ſhould do amiſs to make it manifeſt; but when it is open in the ſight and view of all men, who can complain juſtly?</p>
            <p>Now let the Reader obſerve; thus ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If one of themſelves, even a prophet of their own ſaith it, therefore this witneſs is true,</hi> Tit. 1. 12, 13. and indeed what have many of their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48903:14"/> ſaid leſs in the firſt and ſecond admonition to the Parliament in the 13. year of Q. <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> reign, 1530. p. 49. in theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">What encouragement and favour have they ſhewed the Papiſts, when the Papiſts have been complained upon? how have they opened their ears (meaning the Biſhops) to their complaints againſt the miniſters, and ſhut their ears when the Papiſts have been complained upon? yea, ſome have ſaid, that conformable Papiſts were more tollerable than theſe Preciſians and godly men that ſeek for Reformation: Who be their Chancellors but moſt ſuſpected Papiſts? And where have they their moſt countenance, but of the Biſhops? I hear not of one of them, but is a briber. Who be their Sumners, but very Varlets? What are their Canoniſts but ſuſpected Papiſts? They wring their brethren if they be Gods children, and let the papiſts go ſcot-free, or be puniſhed but lightly. And what more is expreſly forbidden in the Scriptures, than thoſe names and offices which Chriſt hath forbidden his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be called, gracious Lords, <hi>Luke 21. 25. 28.</hi>
               </q> and many ſuch things worth the obſerving by all thoſe that have the Book by them.</p>
            <p>Thus I hope it is ſufficiently proved, that it is not liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that is the cauſe <hi>Popery</hi> hath increaſed in this land, but the groſs abuſes in the Doctors Church and Miniſtry. Moreover, if the Lord of old was not againſt liberty of conſcience in things ſpiritual, who compelled not the <hi>Gibeonites, Hittites, Gergaſhistes,</hi> or unclean Iſraelites that lived in the Lords Land, to keep his Faſt or Feaſt, or to do any part of his worſhip by the Civil Sword no more it is the mind of God under the Goſpel, <hi>Joſh. 16. 10. Lev. 15. 44. 2 Cor. 7. 8.</hi> neither could the Doctor have been ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that, or ſo plain a Goſpel doctrine, if his ſtudy were ſpent as much in the book of God, as in Hiſtory; for as much as Chriſt Jeſus, Creator and Lord of the whole earth, hath divided it freely to all Nations under the whole heavens, to dwell therein, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the bounds of their habitations, <hi>Gen. 10. 32. Acts 17. 26.</hi> and accordingly Chriſt hath expounded the parable, that the field is the world, <hi>Mat. 13. 38.</hi> wherein the good ſeed, children of the kingdom; and the tares, children of the wicked one, are allowed by Chriſt to grow together, though not in the Church, <hi>Mat. 18. 17. 1 Cor. 5. Prov. 25. 4, 5. Gen. 4. 6. Gal. 4. 30.</hi> but in the field (unleſs the Doctor thinks the whole world be the Church)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48903:14"/> until the Harveſt or end of the world; for the Lord doth cauſe his Sun to ſhine on the evil and the good, and ſendeth rain on the juſt and on the unjuſt; how then dare mortal man by perſecution debar his fellow creatures from the liberty given them of God, ſo long as they do to all men as they would have others do to them? but when they do otherwiſe contrary to the ſecond table of Gods law, the Magiſtrate beareth not the ſword in vain, <hi>Rom. 13. 4. For he is the miniſter of God, a revenger, to execute wrath upon him that doth evil:</hi> ſurely then it may be ſaid to ſuch that ſeek to have their brethren perſecuted, they do therein as it were call for fire to come down from heaven to deſtroy them, <hi>Luke 9. 54.</hi> unto ſuch Chriſt ſaith, they know not what ſpirit they are of: <hi>for who is he, O man, that maketh thee to differ from another?</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 7. or haſt thou any good in thee ſince thy fall, that thou haſt not received? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man ought to know, that it is God only <hi>which perſwadeth Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to dwell in the tents of Shem,</hi> Gen. 9 27. ſo that to force men to be religious before God giveth them faith, is to make a Church of hypocrites, ſuch as all perſecuting ſpirits are; and this ſpirit was ever ſeen in Lordly Prelates and their accomplices, as by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience the fore-named Chriſtians felt, whom the Dr. hath reproached; as it is to be ſeen in a Petition in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days they preſented to the Parliament aforementioned, ſeaſonable in this day for all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to be acquainted with, concerning the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops cruelty to the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> then, that would neither touch, taſt, nor handle any popiſh tradition or corruption either in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry or Worſhip. The Petition word for word as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The humble, moſt earneſt, and lamentable Complaint and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the perſecuted Church and Servants of Chriſt called</hi> Browniſts.</p>
            <p>THE moſt high God, poſſeſſor of heaven and earth, bringeth at this preſent before your Lordſhips and Wiſdoms, Right Honourable, his own cauſe, his own people, and his own ſworn and moſt treacherous enemies, together with the moſt ſhameful uſage of his truth and ſervants, that ever hath been heard of in the days of <hi>Sions</hi> profeſſed peace and tranquility.</p>
            <p>His cauſe and people he offereth unto your conſideration and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in our profeſſion and perſons, his enemies and their outrage
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48903:15"/> againſt his truth and ſervants in the perſons and bloody proceedings of the Prelates of the Land and their Complices.</p>
            <p>We profeſs the ſame faith and truth of the Goſpel which her <hi>Majeſty</hi> and your Honours, the whole Land, and all the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches under heaven this day do hold and maintain, we go beyond them, being our only fault even in the judgments of our ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical and moſt ſavage enemies, in the deteſtation of all Popery, that moſt fearful Antichriſtian Religion, and draw nearer in ſome points by our practice, unto Chriſts holy order and inſtitution; this is our faith, this is our cauſe in our ſinful hands, and for the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and maintenance of which faith, the forenamed enemies of God detain in their hands within the priſons about <hi>London,</hi> not to ſpeak of other Gaols throughout the Land, about threeſcore and twelve perſons, men and women, young and old, lying in cold, in hunger, in dungeons, in irons; of which number they have taken the Lords day laſt paſt, being the third of the fourth month 1592. about ſome 56. perſons hearing the word of God truly taught, praying and praiſing God for all his favours ſhewed unto us, and unto her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> your Honours, and the whole Land, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring our God to be merciful unto us, and to our gracious <hi>Princeſs</hi> and Countrey; being employed in theſe holy actions, and no other, as the parties who diſturbed us can teſtifie: they were taken in the very ſame place where the perſecuted Church and martyrs were inforced to uſe like exerciſe in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days. The former number are now unbailably committed by the <hi>Prelates</hi> or biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> into cloſe, for the moſt, in ſeveral priſons, as <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> the <hi>Clink,</hi> the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> the <hi>Limbo</hi> or Dungeon in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> the <hi>Fleet,</hi> the <hi>Marſhalſey,</hi> the <hi>Counter,</hi> the <hi>White-Lyon:</hi> wherein we willingly acknowledg the lot and inheritance in this life, of our forefathers, and brethren, and holy martyrs of the former age, and the entailed <hi>Aceldema,</hi> or blood ſucceſſion of the See of <hi>London,</hi> and that whole Lineage. Well, here our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren lye, how long Lord holy and true, thou knoweſt! in dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in hunger, in cold, and in nakedneſs, with all outward diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for theſe bloody men will allow them neither meat, drink, fire, lodging, nor ſuffer any whoſe hearts the Lord would ſtir up for their relief, to have any acceſs unto them, purpoſing belike to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them unto death, as they have done ſeventeen or eighteen others in the ſame noiſome Gaols within theſe ſix years; the wife and husband now taken by them, they permit not to be in the ſame,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48903:15"/> but have ſent them to be cloſely kept in other Priſons; what the poor Family doth at home in the mean time, your Lordſhips may conſider, and juſtly pity: Some of the Company had not one Peny about them when they were ſent to Priſon, nor any thing being abroad, which is the caſe of moſt of them, if not all, to procure themſelves and their poor Families any maintenance, ſave only their handy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Trades; whereby it is come to paſs, that theſe enemies of God, do not only ſtarve and undo a number of men in Priſons, but even a lamentable company of poor Orphans and Servants abroad; their unbridled ſlanders, their lawleſs privy ſearches, their violent breaking open and rifling our Houſes, their lamentable and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous uſage of Women and young Children in theſe hoſtile aſſaults, and ever robbing and taking away whatſoever they think meet from us. In this Caſe their unappeaſed, mercileſs purſuit of us from our Houſes, Trades, Wife and Children, eſpecially from the holy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Saints and Church of God, we are forced to omit, leſt we ſhould be over-tedious to your Lordſhips; but their deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings this way towards us is ſo woful, Right Honourable, as we may truly demand, with grief of heart, whether the forreign enemy, or our own Native Country men do poſſeſs and bear Rule over us in our dear and native Country?</p>
            <p>Their whole dealings herein is moſt barbarous, inhumane, but eſpecially moſt Antichriſtian, and ſuch as exceed the cruelty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Popiſh profeſſed Tyrants and perſecutors: The Records of the Heathen perſecution under <hi>Nero, Trajan, Deſius, Gallianus, Maximinian,</hi> can ſcant afford us any examples of like cruelty and havock; for the Heathen <hi>Romans</hi> would murther openly and profeſſedly; theſe godleſs men have put the blood of War about them in the Day of Peace and Truce, which the whole Land pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to hold with Chriſt Jeſus and his Servants. Biſhop <hi>Bouner, Story, Weſton</hi> dealt not after this ſort, for thoſe whom they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloſe, they brought them in ſhort ſpace openly into <hi>Smithfield</hi> to end their miſery, and to begin their never-ending joy; whereas Biſhop <hi>Elmor,</hi> Doctor <hi>Stanhope,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Juſtis Yong,</hi> with the reſt of that perſecuting and blood-thirſty faculty, will do neither of theſe; no Fellon, no Murderer, no Traytor in the Land are thus dealt with.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48903:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48903:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48903:17"/>
            <p>There are many of us by the Mercies of God ſtill out of their hands; the former exerciſe and profeſſion we purpoſe not to leave by the aſſiſtance of God: We have as good warrant to reject the ordinances of Antichriſt, and labour for the recovery of Chriſts Holy Ordinances, as our Fathers in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days. If our Cauſe were truly known to her Majeſty and your wiſdoms, we ſhould find greater favour than they did; whereas our ſtate now is far more lamentable, and therefore we humbly and earneſtly crave of her Majeſty and your Lordſhips both, for our ſelves in miſerable captivity, but juſt and equal tryal according to her Majeſties Laws; if we prove not our Adverſaries to be in a moſt peſtilent and godleſs condition, both in regard of their offices and their proceedings in them, and our ſelves to be in the right way, we deſire not to have the benefit of her Majeſties true and faithful Subjects, which of all earthly favours, we account it to be one of the greateſt. Are we Malefactors? are we anywiſe undutiful to our Prince? maintain we any errors? Let us then be judicially convicted thereof, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Civil Authority; but let not theſe bloody men, both accuſe, condemn, and cloſe murder us after this ſort, contrary to all Law, Equity and Conſcience, where alone they are the Plaintiff, the Accuſers, the Judges and the Executioners of their moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, barbarous Tyranny.</p>
            <p>They ſhould not, by the Laws of the Land, go any further in caſes of Religion, than their own Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, and then refer us to the Civil Powers; their fore-fathers, <hi>Gardener, Bonner, Story,</hi> dealt thus equally, and we crave but their equity. Oh! let her excellent Majeſty our Sovereign, and your wiſdoms, conſider and accord unto this our juſt Petition, for ſtreams of innocent blood are likely to be ſpilt in ſecret by theſe blood-thirſty men, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and your Honours, do take order with their moſt cruel and inhumane proceedings.</p>
            <p>We crave for all of us, but liberty either to dye openly, or to live openly in the Land of our Nativity; if we deſerve death, it beſeemeth the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of Juſtice not to ſee us cloſely murdered, yea, ſtarved to death with hunger and cold, and ſtilled in loathſom Dungeons: If we be guiltleſs, we crave but the benefit of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, that we may have peace to ſerve our God and our Prince, in the place and ſepulchers of our Fathers.</p>
            <p>Thus proteſting our Innocency, complaining of Violence and Wrong, and crying for Juſtice on the behalf, and in the name of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48903:17"/> that Righteous Judge, the God of Equity and Juſtice, we continue our Prayers unto Him for her <hi>Majeſty</hi> and your Honours, whoſe hearts we beſeech him to incline towards this our moſt equal and juſt ſuit, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>The condition of thoſe poor Chriſtians being ſo deplorable, ſome may marvel the Queen, ſo worthy a Princeſs, did not relieve them! But it is no marvel, when it is conſidered on the other hand, where the ſpiritual Lords, ſo called, bear ſway in a Nation, no pity can be expected, or favour to Chriſts faithful Servants, that without reſpect to perſons, worſhip God, and ſpeak his truth as it is in Jeſus. But, God be thanked, their power hath been for many years abated, and we have ſeen the days of peace to worſhip God, which they whom the world was not worthy of longed to ſee, and many of them obtained it not, but were taken away to a better inheritance, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things duly weighed, the Chriſtian Reader may ſee what a perſecuting ſpirit theſe Lordly Prelates are of, and whether the Doctor is not of the ſame, by all the ſymptoms of his Book, as an Herald ſounding before his Brethren and Reverend Fathers, what he hath longed to be at, were the Carpenter removed out of the way that hath frayed ſhort, <hi>Zach. 1.</hi> the Horns of their power, that as yet they cannot uſe like cruelty, in that meaſure their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours have done, as hath been ſeen. Now why the Doctor hath incouraged himſelf in this evil work, to ſmite with the tongue. <hi>Jer. 18. 18.</hi> or fiſt of wickedneſs, <hi>Iſa. 58. 4.</hi> his diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as he calls them, in this his Dragon-like War, by caſting out of his mouth, <hi>Rev. 12. 16.</hi> with <hi>Pſal. 69. 14, 15.</hi> floods of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches againſt Gods faithful Servants, becauſe they kept the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, <hi>John 15. 14.</hi> and have the teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev. 12. 17.</hi> unles <hi>Deog</hi> like, he hopeth, <hi>Pſal. 52. 4, 7.</hi> to obtain more favour, or with <hi>Baalam,</hi> to gain ſome greater promotion, <hi>Numb. 22. 37.</hi> than yet he hath, or rewards for his pains; And is this the work of one that accounteth himſelf a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Goſpel? Surely it no whit agreeth to the word Goſpel, which ſignifieth glad tidings of peace, as is the work of all true Goſpel Miniſters, ſaith Chriſt, in his firſt Sermon, <hi>Bleſſed is the peace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> yea, alſo between man and man, even among brethren how good it is! <hi>Pſal. 133.</hi> Thus ought no Chriſtian to hate the perſon of his very enemy, much leſs whom Chriſt calleth his friends for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48903:18"/> his Commandments, <hi>John 15. 14.</hi> And that theſe Chriſtians whom the Doctor reproachfully calleth <hi>Browniſts,</hi> were ſuch, is evident by their Faith and Practice, in their deſcription of the true viſible Church of Chriſt, which the ſuffering Chriſtians publiſhed to the year 1589. as followeth word for word, taken out of their Printed Copy.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A true deſcription out of the Word of God, of the viſible Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS there is but <hi>(a)</hi> one God and Father of all, one Lord over all, and one Spirit; ſo is there but <hi>(b)</hi> one Truth, one Faith, one Salvation, one Church, called in one Hope, joyned in one Profeſſion, guided by one <hi>(c)</hi> Rule, even the Word of the moſt high. <hi>(a) Geneſ. 1. 1. Exod. 20. 3. (b) 1 Tim. 2. 4. Phil. 1. 27. Epheſ. 2. 18. John 8. 41. (c) Deut. 6. 25. Rom. 10. 8. 2 Tim. 3. 15. Joh. 8. 51. 1 Joh. 2. 3, 4, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Church as it is univerſally underſtood, containeth in it all the elect of God that have been, are, or ſhall be: But being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered more particularly, as it is ſeen in this preſent world, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of a company and fellowſhip of <hi>(a)</hi> faithful and holy people <hi>(b)</hi> gathered in the name of Chriſt Jeſus, their only <hi>(c)</hi> King, <hi>(d)</hi> Prieſt, and <hi>(e)</hi> Prophet, <hi>(f)</hi> worſhipping him aright, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>(g)</hi> peaceably and quietly governed by his Officers and Laws, <hi>(h)</hi> keeping the unity of faith in the bond of peace and <hi>(i)</hi> love unfained. <hi>(a) Gen. 17. 1 Pet. 1. 2. Rev. 7. 9. 1 Cor. 10. 3. Joh. 17. 10, 20. (b) Pſal. 111. 1. and 149. 1. Iſa. 62. 12. Epheſ. 1. 1. 1 Cor. 1. 2. Deut. 14. 2. (c)Deut. 12. 5. Joh. 6. 37. and 3. 14. and 12. 32. Luk. 17. 37. (d) Gen. 44. 10. Pſal. 45. 6. Zach 9. 9. Heb. 1. 8. (e) Rom. 8. 34. Joh. 17. Heb. 5. 9. and 8. 1. and 4. 14. (f) Deut. 18. 15. Matt. 17. 5. Heb. 1. 2. Gen. 14. 18. (g) Exod. 20. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. Lev. 10. 5. Joh. 4. 23. (h) Matt. 11. 29. 1 Cor. 11. 16. Mark 13. 34. Rev. 22. 9. (i) Epheſ. 4. 3. 1 Cor. 1. 13. Mark 9. 50 John 13. 34. 1 Cor. 13. 4. 1 Pet. 1. 22. 1 John 3. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48903:18"/>
            <p>Moſt <hi>(a)</hi> joyful, excellent and glorious things, are every where in the Scriptures ſpoken of this Church. It is called the <hi>(b)</hi> City, <hi>(c)</hi> Houſe, <hi>(d)</hi> Temple, and <hi>(e)</hi> Mountain of the Eternal God: the <hi>(f)</hi> Choſen Generation, the Holy Nation, the peculiar Peopls, the <hi>(g)</hi> Vineyard, the <hi>(h)</hi> Garden encloſed, the Spring ſhut up, the ſealed Fountain, the Orchard of Pomgranates with ſweet fruits, the <hi>(i)</hi> heritage, the <hi>(k)</hi> Kingdom of Chriſt: yea, his <hi>(l)</hi> Siſter, his Love, his Spouſe, his <hi>(m)</hi> Queen, and his <hi>(n)</hi> Body, the joy of the whole Earth. To this ſociety is the <hi>(o)</hi> Covenant and all the Promiſes made of <hi>(p)</hi> Peace, of Love, and of <hi>(q)</hi> Salvation, of the <hi>(r)</hi> Preſence of God, of his Graces, of his Power, and of his <hi>(ſ)</hi> Protection. <hi>(a) Pſal 87. 3. (b) Ibid. (c) 1 Tim. 3. 15. Heb. 3. 6. (d) 1 Cor. 3. 17. (e) Iſa. 2. 2. Micah 4. 1. Zach. 8. 3. (f) 1 Pet. 2. 9. (g) Iſa. 5. 1.</hi> and 27. 2 <hi>(h) Song 4. 12. Iſa. 51. 3. (i) Iſa. 19. 25. (k) Micha. 5. 2. Matt. 3. 2. Joh. 3. 5. (l) Song. 5. 2. (m) Pſal. 45. 9. (n) 1 Cor. 22. 27, Epheſ. 1. 23. (o) Gal. 4. 28. Rom. 9. 24. (p) Pſal. 147. 14. 2 Theſ. 3. 16. (q) Iſa. 46. 13. Zach. 14. 17. (r) Iſa 60. Ezech. 47. Zach. 4. 12. (ſ) Ezech. 48. 35 Matt. 28. 20. Iſa. 62.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely if this Church be conſidered in her parts, it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear moſt beautiful, yea, moſt wonderful, and even <hi>(a)</hi> raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſenſes to conceive, much more to behold, what then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſo bleſſed a Communion! For behold, her <hi>(b)</hi> King and Lord, is the King of Peace, and Lord himſelf of all Glory. She enjoyeth moſt holy and heavenly. <hi>(c)</hi> Laws, moſt faithful and vigilant <hi>(d)</hi> Paſtors, moſt ſincere and pure <hi>(e)</hi> Teachers, moſt careful and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>(f)</hi> Governors, moſt diligent and truſty <hi>(g)</hi> Deacons, moſt loving and ſober <hi>(h)</hi> Relievers, and a moſt <hi>(i)</hi> humble, meek, obedient, faithful, and loving people, every <hi>(k)</hi> ſtone li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, elect and precious, every ſtone hath his beauty, his <hi>(l)</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and his <hi>(m)</hi> order. All bound to <hi>(n)</hi> edifie one another, exhort, reprove, and comfort one another <hi>(o)</hi> lovingly as to their own members, <hi>(p)</hi> faithful as in the eyes of God. <hi>(a) Song 6. 4, 9. (b) Iſa. 62. 11. Joh. 12. 15. Heb. 2. 7, 8. (c) Matt. 11. 30. 1 John 5. 3 (d) Epheſ. 4. 11. Acts 20. (e) Rom. 12. 7. (f) 1 Cor. 12. 21. Rom 12. 8. (g) Acts 6. (h) Rom 12. 8. (i) Matt. 15. 5 Ezek. 36. 38. Iſa. 60. 8. Deut. 18. 9 13. (k) 1 Pet. 2. 5. 1 King. 7. 9. Zach. 14. 21. (l) Gal. 6, 2. (m) 1 Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48903:19"/> 
               <hi>12. Rom. 12. 3,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(n) Heb. 10. 24. (o) Lev. 19. 17. 1 Theſ. 4. 9. (p) Col. 3. 23. 1 John 3. 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No <hi>(a)</hi> Office here is ambitiouſly affected, no <hi>(b)</hi> Law wrong fully wreſted or <hi>(c)</hi> wilfully neglected, no <hi>(d)</hi> Truth hid or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, <hi>(e)</hi> every one here hath freedom and power (not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing the peaceable order of the Church) to utter his complaints and griefs, and freely to reprove the tranſgreſſion and errors without exception of perſons. <hi>(a) 2 Cor. 2. 17. 3 John 9. (b) 1 Tim. 4. 2, 3.</hi> and 5. 21. and 6. 14. <hi>Gal. 6. 12. (c) 1 Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. (d) Jer. 23. 28. 1 Tim. 3. 15. (e) 1 Cor. 6.</hi> and 14. 30. <hi>Col. 4. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is no <hi>(a)</hi> intruſion or climbing up another way into the ſheepfold, than <hi>(b)</hi> by the holy and free election of the Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and free people, and that according to the Lords Ordinance, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves by faſting and prayer before the Lord, craving the direction of his holy Spirit, for the trial and approving of Gifts, <hi>&amp;c. (a) Joh. 10. 1. (b) Acts 1. 23.</hi> and 6. 3. and 14. 23.</p>
            <p>Thus they orderly proceed to Ordination by faſting and prayer, in which <hi>(a)</hi> action the Apoſtles uſed laying on of hands. Thus hath every one of the people intereſt in the election and ordination of their Officers, as alſo in the adminiſtration of their Offices, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>(b)</hi> tranſgreſſion, offence, abuſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having an eſpecial care unto the inviolable order of the Church, as is aforeſaid. <hi>(a) 1 Tim. 4. 14.</hi> and 5. 22. <hi>(b) Luk. 17. 3. Rom. 16. 17. Col. 4. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe in this Church they have holy <hi>(a)</hi> Laws, as limits and bonds, which it is lawful at no hand to tranſgreſs. They have Laws to direct them in the choice of every Officer, what kind of men the Lord will have. Their Paſtour muſt be apt to <hi>(b)</hi> teach, no young Schollar, <hi>(c)</hi> able to divide the word aright, <hi>(d)</hi> holding faſt that faithful word, according to Doctrine, that he may be able alſo to exhort, rebuke, improve with wholfom Doctrine, and to convince them that ſay againſt it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He muſt be <hi>(e)</hi> a man that loveth good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he muſt be wiſe, righteous, holy, temperate; he muſt be of life unreprovable, as Gods Steward; he muſt be generally well reported of, and one that ruleth his own houſhould under obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48903:19"/> with all honeſty; he muſt be modeſt, humble, meek, gentle and loving; he muſt be a man of great <hi>(f)</hi> patience, compaſſion, labour and diligence; he muſt always be careful and watchful over the flock whereof the Lord hath made him overſeer, with all wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs and chearfulneſs, not holding his office in reſpect of perſons, but doing his duty to every ſoul, as he will anſwer before the chief Shepherd, &amp;c. <hi>(a) Matt. 5. 19. 1 Tim. 1. 18. (b) Deut. 33. 10. Mal. 2. 7. 1 Tim. 3. 1,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(c) 2 Tim. 2. 15. (d)Tit. 1. 9. 2 Tim. 4. 2. (e) Tit. 1. 7, 8. (f) Numb. 12. 3, 7 Iſa. 50. 4, 5, 6. Jer. 3. 15. Ezek. 34. 18. Acts 20. 1 Pet. 5. 1, 2, 3, 4. 1 Tim. 5. 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Doctor or Teacher muſt be a man apt to teach, able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Word of God aright, and to deliver ſound and wholeſom Doctrine from the ſame, ſtill building upon that ſound ground work; he muſt be mighty in the Scriptures, able to convince the gainſayers, and careful to deliver his Doctrine pure, ſound and plain, not with curioſity or affectation, but ſo that it may edifie the moſt ſimple, approving it to every mans Conſcience; he muſt be of life unrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, one that can govern his own houſhould, he muſt be of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſober, temperate, modeſt, gentle and loving, <hi>&amp;c. 1. Tim. 3. Titus 1. 2 Tim. 2. 15. 1 Cor. 17.</hi> and 2, 4.</p>
            <p>Their Elders muſt be of wiſdom and judgment endued with the Spirit of God, able to diſcern between cauſe and cauſe, between plea and plea, and accordingly to prevent and redreſs evils, always vigilant and intending to ſee the Statutes, Ordinances, and Laws of God kept in the Church, and that not only by the people in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. but to ſee the Officers do their duties. Theſe men muſt be of life likewiſe unreprovable, governing their own families orderly, they muſt be alſo of manners ſober, gentle, modeſt, loving, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, <hi>&amp;c. Numb. 11. 24, 25. 2 Chron. 19. 8. Acts 15. 1 Tim. 3.</hi> and <hi>5. chap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Deacons muſt be men of honeſt report, having the myſtery of the ſaith in a pure conſcience, endued with the Holy Ghoſt; they muſt be grave, temperate, not given to exceſs, nor to filthy lucre. <hi>Acts 6. 3. 1 Tim. 3. 8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Relievers, or Widows, muſt be women of Sixty years of age at the leaſt, for avoiding of inconveniences; they muſt be well reported of for good works, ſuch as have nouriſhed their Children, ſuch as have not been harbarous to Strangers; diligent and ſervice able to the Saints, compaſſionate and helpful to them in adverſity, given
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48903:20"/> to every good work, continuing in ſupplications and prayers night and day. <hi>1 Tim. 5. 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Officers muſt firſt be duely proved, then if they be found blameleſs, adminiſter, <hi>&amp;c. 1 Tim. 3. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the perſons, gifts, conditions, manners, life, and proof of theſe Officers is ſet down by the Holy Ghoſt; ſo are their Offices limited, ſevered, and divers. <hi>1 Cor. 12. 12, 18, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Paſtours office is, to feed the ſheep of Chriſt in green and wholeſom paſtures of his Word, and lead them to the ſtill waters, even to the pure Fountain and River of life. He muſt guide and keep thoſe ſheep by that heavenly ſheephook and paſtoral ſtaff of the Word, thereby drawing them to him, thereby looking into their ſouls, even into their moſt ſecret thoughts: Thereby diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their diſeaſes, and thereby curing them; applying to every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe a fit and convenient medicine, and according to the quality and danger of the diſeaſe, give warning to the Church, that they may orderly proceed to excommunication. Further, he muſt by this his ſheephook watch over and defend his flock from ravenous beaſts and the Wolf, and take the little Foxes, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal. 23. Lev. 10. 10, 11. Numb. 18. 1. Ezek 44. 23,</hi> and 33, and 34. <hi>Joh. 21. 15. Acts 20. 28. 1 Pet. 5, 1. 4 Zach. 11. 7. Rev. 22. 2. Luk. 12. 42. 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5. Heb. 4. 12. John 10. 11, 12. Song. 2. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctors Office is already ſet down in his deſcription: His ſpecial care muſt be, to build upon the only true groundw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ork, gold, ſilver, and precious ſtones, that his work may endure the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the fire, and by the light of the ſame fire, reveal the Timber, Hay and Stubble of falſe Teachers: he muſt take diligent heed to keep the Church from errors. And further, he muſt deliver his Doctrine ſo plainly, ſimply and purely, that the Church may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with the increasing of God, and grow up unto him which is the Head, Chriſt Jeſus. 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 11, 12. Levit. 10. 10. Ezek. 33. 1, 2,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and 44. 24. Mal. 2. 6. 1 Cor. 3. 11. 1 Cor. 1. 17. 1 Tim. 4. 16.</hi> and 6. 20. <hi>Epheſ. 2. 20. Heb. 6. 1. 2 Pet. 2. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Office of the Ancients is expreſſed in their deſcription: Their eſpecial care muſt be, to ſee the Ordinances of God truly taught and practiſed, as well by the Officers in doing their duty uprightly, as to ſee that the people obey willingly and readily. It is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſee the Congregation holily and quietly ordered, and no way diſturbed by the contentious and diſobedient, froward and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48903:20"/> not taking away the liberty of the leaſt, but upholding the right of all, wiſely judging of times and circumſtances. They muſt be ready aſſiſtants to the Paſtor and Teachers, helping to bear their burden, but not intruding into their Office. <hi>Numb. 11. 16. Deut. 1. 13.</hi> and 16. 18. <hi>2 Chron. 19. 8. Exod. 39. 42. 1 Tim. 3. 15. 2 Tim. 1. 13. 1 Cor. 11. 16.</hi> and 14. 33. <hi>Gal. 2. 4, 5, 14. Col. 4. 16, 17. Acts 20, 1. Pet. 5. 1. Rom. 12. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deacons office is, faithfully to gather and collect by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Church, the goods and benevolence of the faithful, and by the ſame direction diligently and truſtily to diſtribute them according to the neceſſity of the Saints. Further, they muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and conſider of the proportion of the wants both of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and other poor, and accordingly relate unto the Church, that proviſion may be made. <hi>Acts 6. Rom. 12. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Relievers and Widows office is, to miniſter to the ſick, lame, weary and diſeaſed, ſuch helpful comforts as they need, by watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tending and helping them: Further, they muſt ſhew good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the younger Women, in ſober, modeſt and godly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, avoiding idleneſs, vain talk, and light behaviour. <hi>Rom. 12. 8. 1 Tim. 5. 9.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe Officers, though they be divers and ſeveral, yet are they not ſevered, leſt there ſhould be a diviſion in the body; but they are as members of the body, having the ſame care one of another, jointly doing their ſeveral duties to the ſervice of the ſaints, and to the edification of the Body of Chriſt, till we all meet together in the perfect meaſure of the fulneſs of Chriſt, by whom all the Body being in the mean while thus coupled and knit together by every joynt for the furniture thereof, according to the effectual power which is in the meaſure of every part, receiveth increaſe of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, unto the edifying of it ſelf in love; neither can any of theſe Offices be wanting, without grievous lameneſs, and apparent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Body, yea, violent injury to the Head Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Luke 9 46, 47, 48. John 13. 12--17. 1 Cor. 12. 12, 25, 28. Eph. 4. 11, 12, 13, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus this holy Army of Saints is marſhalled here in earth by theſe Officers, under the conduct of their glorious Emperor CHRIST, that victorious Michael. Thus it marcheth in this moſt heavenly order, and gracious array, againſt all enemies both bodily and ghoſtly: peaceable in it ſelf as <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> terrible to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as an Army with Banners; triumphing over their tyranny with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48903:21"/> patience, their cruelty with meekneſs, and over Death it ſelf with dying. Thus through the blood of that ſpotleſs Lamb, and that Word of their Teſtimony, they are more than Conquerors, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the head of the Serpent: yea, through the power of his Word, they have power to caſt down Satan like lightning; to tread upon Serpents and Scorpions; to caſt down ſtrong holds, and every thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt God. The Gates of Hell, and all the principalities and powers of the world ſhall not prevail againſt it. <hi>Rom. 12. 1 Cor. 12. Rev. 14. 1, 2. Song 6. 3. Rev. 12. 11. Luke 10. 18, 19. 2 Cor. 10 5. Mat. 16. 18. Rom. 8. 38, 39.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, He hath given them the keys of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that whatſoever they bind on earth by his Word, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever they looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven. <hi>Mat. 16. 19. John 20. 23. Mat. 18. 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this power which Chriſt hath given unto his Church, and to every member of his Church to keep it in order, he hath not left it to their diſcretions and luſts to be uſed or neglected as they will, but in his laſt Will and Teſtament he hath ſet down both an order of proceeding, and an end to which it is uſed. <hi>Mat. 16. 16, 19.</hi> and 18. 15, 16, 17, 18. and 28. 20. <hi>Deut. 12. 31, 32. Rev. 22. 18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the fault be private, holy and loving admonition and reproof is to be uſed, with an inward deſire and earneſt care to win their Brother; but if he will not hear, yet to take two or three other brethren with him, whom he knoweth moſt meet for that purpoſe, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, every word may be confirmed: And if he refuſe to hear them, then to declare the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Church, which ought ſeverely and ſharply to reprehend, gravely to admoniſh, and lovingly to perſwade the party offending; ſhewing him the heinouſneſs of his offence, and the danger of his obſtinacy, and the fearful judgments of the Lord. <hi>Lev. 19. 17, 18. Mat. 18. 15. Deut. 19. 15. Mat. 18. 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this, notwithſtanding the Church is not to hold him as an enemy, but to admoniſh him and pray for him as a Brother, proving if at any time the Lord will give him repentance: For this power is not given them to the deſtruction of any, but to the edification of all. <hi>2 Theſ. 3. 15. 2 Cor. 10. 8.</hi> and 13. 10.</p>
            <p>If this prevail not to draw him to repentance, then are they in the Name and Power of the Lord JESUS with the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, reverently in prayer to proceed to excommunication; that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48903:21"/> is, unto the caſting him out of their congregation and fellowſhip, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and protection of the Lord, for his diſobedience and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and committing him to Satan for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the Spirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus, if ſuch be his good will and pleaſure. <hi>Mat. 18. 17. 1 Cor. 5. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, They are to warn the whole Congregation and all other faithful, to hold him as a Heathen and Publican, and to abſtain themſelves from his ſociety, as not to eat or drink with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs it be ſuch as of neceſſity muſt needs, as his Wife, his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Family; yet theſe (if they be members of the Church) are not to joyn to him in any ſpiritual exerciſe. <hi>Mat. 18. 17. 1 Cor. 5. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the offence be publick, the party is publickly to be reproved and admoniſhed; if he then repent not, to proceed to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, as aforeſaid. <hi>1 Tim. 5. 20. Gal. 2. 14. Joſ. 7. 19. 2 Cor. 7. 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The repentance of the party muſt be proportionable to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>viz.</hi> If the offence be publick, publick; if private, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; humbled, ſubmiſſive, ſorrowful, unfeigned, giving glory to the Lord. <hi>Lev. 19. 17, 18. Prov. 10. 12. Rom. 12. 19.</hi> and 13. 10. and 14. 1.</p>
            <p>There muſt great care be had of admonitions, that they be not captious or curious, finding fault where none is, neither yet in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs or reproach; for that were to deſtroy and not to ſave our Brother: but they muſt be carefully done, with prayer going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they muſt be ſeaſoned with truth, gravity, love and peace. <hi>Mat. 18. 15.</hi> and 26. 8. <hi>Gal. 6. 1, 2. 2 Tim. 2. 24. Mark 9. 50. Epheſ. 4. 29 James 5. 15, 19, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, in this Church is an eſpecial care had by every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof, of offences; the ſtrong ought not to offend the weak, nor the weak to judge the ſtrong: but all graces here are given to the ſervice and edification of each other in love and long ſuffering. <hi>Luke 17. 1. Prov. 10. 12. Rom. 14. 13, 19. Gal. 6. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Church is the Truth purely taught, and ſurely kept; here is the Covenant, the Sacraments and Promiſes, the Graces, the Glory, the Preſence, the Worſhip of God, <hi>&amp;c. Gen. 17. Lev. 26. 11, 12. Iſa. 44. 3. Gal. 4. 28.</hi> and 6. 16. <hi>Iſa. 60. 15. Deut. 4. 12, 13. Iſa. 56. 7. 1 Tim. 3. 15. Iſa. 12. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into this Temple entreth no unclean thing, neither whatſoever worketh abominations or lies, but they which are written in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48903:22"/> Lambs Book of life. <hi>Iſa. 62. 1. Ezek. 44. 9. Iſa. 35. 8. Zach. 14. 21. Rev. 21. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But without this CHURCH ſhall be Dogs, and Enchanters, and Whoremongers, and Murderers, and Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh lies. <hi>Rom. 2. 9. Rev 22. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
            <p>Now I leave the prudent to judge whether the Doctor be a friend or an enemy to Chriſts Truth and holy order of worſhip, and alſo to his Servants, by calling their Books or Writings ſeditious; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is high time for the Doctors followers to beware of ſuch a guide for their ſouls. Yea, and whether ſuch a man can be reputed a Chriſtian, that calleth the way of Gods Worſhip, ſo agreable to Chriſt's laſt Will and Teſtament, ſeditious? Yea, I ſay it is time, as they tender their Souls eternal happineſs, to examine their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate in worſhip to God, and meaſure the ſame by the golden ſeed of Gods Word, <hi>Rev. 11. 1.</hi> to ſee if it agree to the deſcription of the viſible Church aforeſaid, collected out of the holy Scripture, both in the Miniſtry, Ordinances and Order, as Chriſt Jeſus hath appointed; and for the better obſervation in every particular, and fundamental grounds therein, to note theſe four things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> As every building muſt have a foundation, ſo every true Church muſt have Chriſt for the foundation thereof, <hi>1 Cor. 3. 11. Mat. 16. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The inſtrument in this building muſt be the written Word of God, to wit, the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets, 2. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly</hi> The matter in this building muſt be viſible Saints, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> The way to begin this building muſt be anſwerable to the figurative building of Tabernacle and Temple, that were built of the choiceſt things, and coſtly, <hi>1 Kings 5. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo, anſwerable hereunto, the ſpiritual Temple was built of elect, precious, living ſtones, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 5.</hi> as was foretold in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>I will lay thy ſtones with fair colours, and thy foundation with ſaphire, and all thy borders with pleaſant ſtones,</hi> Iſa. 54. 11. 6. 17, 21.</p>
            <p>2. As the materials of the Temple and Tabernacle were all made fit before they were joyned together, ſo that there may be neither Hammer, <hi>1 Kings. 6. 7.</hi> nor any tool of Iron heard in the building. Even ſo in the ſpiritual, <hi>John</hi> firſt preached in the Wilderneſs, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſquaring a people by the Ax of Gods Word; ſo that the crookedneſs by nature in Gods Elect, was made ſtraight; and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48903:22"/> rough places plain, <hi>Iſa. 40 3. Mat. 3. 3.</hi> by being made new, creatures, <hi>2 Cor. 5. 17.</hi> born again, ſo made fit for the Kingdom of God, <hi>John 3. 5.</hi> And this was Gods way in Grace and Nature in all the Apoſtles, the wiſe Maſter-builder, firſt in the Wilderneſs of the wold by the Preaching the Word to convince, and by it the Lord converting, and then by voluntary profeſſion (not by might or power of man, <hi>Zach 4. 6.)</hi> but by the Spirit of God were they joyned together, by the Covenant of Grace in Chriſt, with him their Lord ſpiritual, Head and Husband of the Body, the Church. For ſo it is written, <hi>As a young man marrieth a virgin, ſo ſhall thy ſons marry thee,</hi> Iſa. 62. 5. 2 Cor. 11. 2. Acts 2. 45. And thus ſaith the Scriptures, <hi>Prepare thy work without, make it fit for thy ſelf in the field; and after build thine houſe,</hi> Prov. 24. 27.</p>
            <p>But how contrary to this heavenly pattern was the Doctors. Church conſtituted in every part, the examiner may ſee, if it were not too long here to inſert; but I refer the Reader to <hi>Henry Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth's Counterpoiſon,</hi> page 205. 127. comparing therewith Mr. <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Acts and Monuments, Edit. 5.</hi> page 1187. 1190. 1184. and for noting theſe and ſuch-like things of the Doctors Church and Miniſtry, the Doctor beſpattereth Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> in his Book with Words; ſo that like <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> his hand is againſt every good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>Gen. 16. 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, though the beginning of this ſpiritual building afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, it is but ſmall compared to a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>Mat. 13. 31.</hi> the day of ſmall things, <hi>Zech. 4. 10.</hi> yet not to be deſpiſed, if but two or three are gathered together in Chriſts name which is his Law, Iſa. 42. 4. <hi>Mat. 12. 21.</hi> in the holy order of his Goſpel, to worſhip God by Chriſts direction, they have the promiſe of Gods preſence to be with them, <hi>Mat. 18. 20.</hi> ſo waiting on the Lord, until he multiply them to be not a few, <hi>Jer. 30. 19.</hi> even like the flock of his paſture, <hi>Ezek. 34. 31. Acts 2. 47.</hi> So that then out of themſelves the Lord hath given them direction to chuſe ſome into the office of Paſtor and Teacher, with Elders and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons as aforeſhewed in the deſcription of the true Church; unto which Aſſembly thus gathered together in holy order, Chriſt Jeſus is their Prophet repreſented (in the offices of Paſtor and Teacher, together with the membral right of the men-members in Propheſie by the word taught among them) that they may diſcern ſin, <hi>Rom. 7. 7.</hi> and righteouſneſs, <hi>Phil. 3. 9. 2dly.</hi> Chriſt is a Prieſt unto them, working upon the will and affections, killing them a ſacrifices,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48903:23"/> 
               <hi>Heb. 9. 11. Rom. 12. 1.</hi> that ſo a reaſonable creature, by the operation of true faith, may be given up to God in his ſervice, <hi>Joh. 4. 23. 3dly.</hi> Chriſt is a King to them, <hi>Pſal. 2. 6.</hi> by his power, <hi>Phil. 2. 5.</hi> that the word taught by prophecy, and applied by prieſthood, may be walked in, <hi>Col. 2. 6.</hi> by a holy life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, <hi>1 Pet. 1. 1 5.</hi> and the whole Church preſerved from all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe power of Sin, the World and the Devil; and after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (ſeeing Chriſts Kingdom is not of this world, <hi>John 18. 36.)</hi> muſt he reign in the Church, until he hath put all his enemies under his feet, <hi>Rev. 19. 16. 1 Cor. 15. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is evident that the Communion in the Doctors Church is not in this way and order of God; the men of his Clergy will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him in their ſecond admonition to the Parliament, page 40. in the <hi>13th</hi> year of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign in the year 1570. who have thus written, <hi>We are ſo ſcarce come to the outward face of a Church rightly reformed, that although ſome truths be taught by ſome Preachers, yet no Preachers may, without danger of the Laws, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the Truths compriſed in the Book of God; it is ſo circumvented and wrapt within the compaſs of ſuch Statutes, ſuch Penalties, ſuch Advertiſements, ſuch Articles, ſuch Canons, ſuch ſober Caveats, and ſuch manifold Pamphlets, that in a manner, if it doth bat peep out behind the skreen, the Laws of the Land, the Book of Common-prayer, the Commiſſioners Advertiſements, the Biſhops Canons,</hi> Linwood's <hi>Provincials, every Biſhops Articles in his Dioceſs, my Lord of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury'<hi>s ſober Caveats, his Licenſes to Preachers, his high Court of Prerogatives, or grave fatherly faculties; theſe together, or the worſt of them, as ſome of them be too bad, may not be broken or offended againſt, but with more danger than to offend againſt the Bible: To theſe ſubſcribing, and ſubſcribing again, and the third time ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing are required; for theſe Preachers and others are indicted, are fined, are impriſoned, are excommunicated, are baniſhed, or have ſome worſe things threatned them; and the Bible, that muſt have no further ſcope than by theſe it is aſſigned. Is this to profeſs Gods Word? Is this Reformation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was fulfilled what was written under the names of Four evil Angels, who ſhould hinder the winds of Gods Spirit ſo much as in them lay, that the true Preaching of the Goſpel-ſhould not blow upon any Tree, <hi>Mat. 3. 10. Luk. 6. 43, 44, 45.</hi> contrary to <hi>Cant. 4. 16.</hi> yet as the Word of God cannot be bound, <hi>Iſa. 55. 11.</hi> there ſtill was by the breathing thereof, <hi>John 3. 8.</hi> a remnant of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48903:23"/> ſanctified ones, Trees of righteouſneſs, who lived and reigned with Chriſt by faith, over Sin, the World and the Devil, all the time of the beaſts reign, <hi>Rev. 20. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore what an evil hath the Doctor done in deſaming ſuch that deſired to walk with Chriſt in his Commands, in worſhip, and refuſed only the inventions of men therein? If he hath done this in blind zeal, in ignorance as did <hi>Saul;</hi> If with him he belong to Gods election, <hi>Rom. 11: 7.</hi> there may be hopes, that as God did change <hi>Saul</hi>'s heart from the ſymptoms of the Letters in his name, which ſignified mortal, ſo perſecuted he the Saints to death, <hi>Acts 7. 58.</hi> and 9. 1, 2. Likewiſe <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> the firſt part of his name ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified cruel or inhumane, the other part, <hi>Pilate,</hi> ſignifying, a man Armed with a <hi>Roman</hi> Dart; ſo was his nature, Chriſt ſuffering under the <hi>Roman</hi> power, was killed by the Dart of <hi>Pilates</hi> ſentence, he being Judge. So likewiſe the drawn Swords of bitter words, <hi>Pſal. 55. 2.</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi> and others then Priſoners in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> is the firſt part of the Doctor's name, through whoſe ſides the Doctor ſtill ſhooteth them againſt all the Nonconformiſts, to the end he might have them <hi>Still-in-fleet,</hi> the natural ſenſe of almoſt every letter of his name; which ſuiteth with the fruits of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, until God giveth him a heart of true repentance, <hi>2 Tim. 2. 25, 26.</hi> that ſo he no longer halt between two opinions, holding the Popiſh office of a Dean; and ſo fight againſt all true Proteſtants that ſhall bear their teſtimony againſt it, and all ſuch like Titles, with mens Traditions in Proteſtant Churches; and on the other hand would ſeem to fight againſt the Papiſts: Surely this man is no <hi>Caleb</hi> nor <hi>Joſhua</hi> in following the Lord fully, but like the man in the Goſpel that deſireth to know what he ſhould do to inherit eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; yet can go no further than he can keep his revenues of great poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Balaam</hi> cold not cozen the Lord, to prevail by his Altar and Sacrifices againſt Gods people, no more ſhall the Doctor with all his bowing, as ſome of his Clergy have been ſaid to have done, and ſo think thereby to prevail againſt the Lords people, no ſure.</p>
            <p>Now who may without partiality, be accounted the moſt trueſt Proteſtants, but thoſe that walk with Chriſt, the moſt neareſt to the Rules of his Goſpel? And is it not for ſo doing, that theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians aforenamed are hated by the Doctor? I'll leave the prudent to judge, and the Doctor to ſhew the contrary if he can. And wherefore are the Judgments of God threatned againſt this Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48903:24"/> Nation, but for the perſecuting, and ſo make a prey of thoſe that depart from iniquity, and bearing their teſtimony againſt all mans inventions in worſhip, as was ſignified in a Warning-piece to the King laſt <hi>April,</hi> 1680, and another to the late Parliament; both to be had where this is ſold, publiſhed by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>Moreover, is this a day for the Doctor to give incouragement to the Magiſtrate, to perſecute their loyal Subjects, for matters of Religion? No ſure, he ſhould have looked to the ſtate of his flock, and ſee how it is commingled with all ſorts of people, as Mr. <hi>Gifford</hi> aforeſaid hath teſtified; when as God hath ſhew'd his Miniſters, that their Work was to put a difference between the holy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, the clean and the unclean; and for the neglect thereof, they were charged with violating Gods Law, <hi>Ezek. 22. 26.</hi> (unleſs the Doctor think there is no unclean viſible wicked liver in his Pariſh.) Again, ſaith the Lord to the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, If thou take the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth; let them return to thee, but return not thou to them,</hi> Jer. 15 19. Even ſo under the Goſpel are the godly forbidden to partake with other mens ſins, <hi>1 Tim. 2. 22.</hi> becauſe in ſperitual Communion, a little Leaven leaveneth the whole lump, <hi>1 Cor. 5. 6. Gal. 5 9. Numb. 19. 22.</hi> So one ſinner ſuffered unpuniſhed, not only deſtroyeth much good, <hi>Prov. 8. 9.</hi> but bringeth that City or Church into a ſnare, <hi>Eccleſ. 9. 18.</hi> As <hi>Joſhuah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſrael, If ye rebel, the Lord will be wrath with the whole congregation,</hi> Joſhua 22. 18. What need then have all that have taken charge of the Souls of a Flock or People, that if they neglect to put Gods Order, <hi>Mat. 18. 1 Cor. 5. Lev. 19. 19.</hi> in practice, to puniſh by the Church cenſures all obſtinate ſinners, God will not only requite it at their hands <hi>Ezekiel 3. 17. 18.</hi> and 33. 7 <hi>Heb. 13. 17. Act. 30.</hi> but for the neglect hereof he will renounce that Churches Candleſtick, <hi>Rev. 2. 5.</hi> ſo fight againſt them <hi>v. 16.</hi> and caſt them into a bed of great tribulation, <hi>Job 33. 19 Rev 2. 2.</hi> and ſpue them utterly from him; ſo that the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Gods marked, ſealed ones, known to be ſuch by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from iniquity, ſhall walk with Chriſt in white, for they are worthy, <hi>Rev. 3. 4. 2 Tim. 2. 19. Ezek. 9. 4. Rev. 7. 3.</hi> when the other that will not be admoniſhed, the Lord ſaith to them; <hi>I have left my heritage, I have given the dearly beloved of my ſoul into the hands of her enemies,</hi> Jer. 11. 15. and 12. 7. <hi>For their inventions have I caſt them out of my houſe,</hi> Hoſea 9. 5. <hi>and have abhorred the excellency of Jacob, and hate all his palaces;</hi> Amos 6. 8. <hi>for the</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48903:24"/> 
               <hi>Lord is of purer eyes than to have fellowſhip with the throne of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; he hath choſen Zion for his dwelling,</hi> Pſal. 132. 13, 14. <hi>Heb. 12. 22. Rev. 14. 1.</hi> his way is holy in all the parts of his ſervice, ſo that the polluted muſt not knowingly dwell there, <hi>Iſa. 35. 8.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they defile the holy things of God, <hi>Lev. 22 3.</hi> therefore God will be ſanctified in all that draw near to him in his <hi>Lev. 10. 3.</hi> for as much as holineſs becometh his houſe for ever, <hi>Pſal. 93. 5.</hi> Now if the Doctor cannot ſee theſe things, and what a confuſion there is, which hath cauſed a great many to ſeparate from his Church for want of Gods Order in it, let him not deſpiſe counſel, ſeeing he that refuſeth inſtruction deſpiſeth his own Soul, <hi>Prov. 15. 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, Seeing we are fallen into the laſt and perilous times, what man of them that hath any thing in him of the Spirit of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but would make it his greateſt work to uſe the uttermoſt of his endeavours to unite the hearts of one Proteſtant to another, in the many difference in point of Religion, that ſo as brethren they may withſtand the common Enemy, even <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the laſt enemies of Gods people, who like unto the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and heathen Nations, <hi>Pſal. 8.</hi> ſay, <hi>Come let us cut them off from being a nation, that the name of Iſrael may be had no more in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi> And is not this the ſigns of the times, when the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Papiſt</hi> are by ſea and land compaſſing the camp of the Saints about in number, like the <hi>Canaanites</hi> Army, <hi>Joſhua 11. 4.</hi> as the ſand on the ſhore, whom God may ſuffer to prevail for the ſins of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, until he hath refin'd them through the fire of affliction, <hi>Zach. 13. 9.</hi> ſo melting the drofs from the ſilver; yet in the end the rod ſhall be broken <hi>Iſa. 10. 5, 24, 25. Pſal. 125. 3.</hi> that ſo they that lead into captivity, ſhall go into captivity; and they that kill with the ſword, ſhall be killed with the ſword, <hi>Rev. 13. 10.</hi> and be mad with ſorrow enough, to ſay with that Heathen King <hi>Adonibezeck,</hi> who cauſed threeſcore and ten Kings to gather meat under his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, having their right thumbs and toes cut off, <hi>As I have done, God hvth requited me,</hi> Judg. 1. 7. If not this way, becauſe the time draweth nigh of Chriſts coming to judgment, then fire ſhall come down from heaven and devour them, <hi>Rev. 20. 9.</hi> yea, ſo ſhall Chriſt come in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>1 Theſ. 1. 8, 9, 10.</hi> in the mean time let all perſecutors read their portion, <hi>Matt. 25. 41. Rev. 14. 9, 10, 11.</hi> and 19. 20. and 21. 8.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48903:25"/>
            <p>And laſtly, If this way of plain dealing liketh not the Doctor, I cannot help it; for with <hi>Elihu</hi> I have learned not to flatter, <hi>Job 32. 22.</hi> nor as ſome men deſire to be ſmoothed in their ſinful ways, <hi>Iſa. 30. 10.</hi> but as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>open rebuke is better than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret love,</hi> Prov. 27. 5. for who could ſleep ſilent, to ſee his brethren that are now at reſt in the Lord, deſamed, when as the Lord ſaith, <hi>the memory of the juſt is bleſſed,</hi> Prov. 10. 7. and <hi>they ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance,</hi> Pſal. 112. 6. whoſe labours ſhine in the world as a comfort to the Lords people when revived, though the ſame be a terror to their enemies, as is ſeen in the Doctor, and ſuch like <hi>John</hi> ſpeaketh of, to ſee more <hi>Seths</hi> raiſed up to maintain the faith faithful <hi>Abels</hi> dyed for, <hi>Rev. 16. 11. Ezek. 37. Rev. 20. 5.</hi> Now the Lord in his infinite mercy bleſs this ſmall mite caſt into the Treaſury of all the Lords true Proteſtant people; and alſo to the Doctor do I deſire it may be for his everlaſting comfort, that ſo the Lord may have the glory, honour and praiſe, in and through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48903:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
